A Guide to the William Branch Porter Collection
Virginia Commonwealth University, Tompkins-McCaw Library
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library
William Branch Porter Collection 1933-1951
Special Collections and Archives, Tompkins-McCaw Library, Virginia Commonwealth University, Richmond, Va.
85/Jan/03
.8 Linear Ft.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restricted to certain records within the collection.
Acquisition Information
Collection discovered in office closet. Donated to library.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Branch Porter was born June 7, 1888 in Amelia County, Virginia. Raised in Powhatan County, he attended Fort Union Military Academy and Hampden-Sydney College. He graduated in medicine from the University College of Medicine in 1911.
Porter taught at the medical schools of Harvard and the University of Pennsylvania before returning to Richmond. During World War 1, Porter served as a member of the cardiovascular unit in Base Hospital 45, a unit made up of doctors from the Medical College of Virginia. After the war, Porter became chief of medical service at Lewis-Gale hospital in Roanoke. In 1927, after two years abroad, he accepted a position as Professor of Medicine at MCV. He became the first full time medical professor in the school's history and focused the school on teaching and medical research.
Porter was a member of many medical societies including the American Medical Association, American Heart Association, and the Medical Society of Virginia. He was Chairman of the Medical Section of the Southern Medical Association in 1935, and served as President of the Richmond Academy of Medicine in 1941. He consulted regularly with the Veterans Administration and the Surgeon General of the Army.
In 1956, after 29 years Porter retired. He was elected emeritus professor and the medical school established the William Branch Porter Professorship in Medicine that same year. An award of a silver plated stethoscope, similar to one given to Porter by Dr. William Osler, is given each year to the top medical school student in internal medicine.
Scope and Content
The collection is limited to committee notes from the academic privileges and admissions committees as well as small amounts of correspondence and reprints of papers. The collection does not contain any information regarding Porter's medical practice or his academic teaching.
Arrangement
The collection follows its original organization.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1951, 1959 (Folder 1)
  This series contains letters regarding hospital business and a primer for testing a doctors knowledge. The primer contains notes and differences of opinion written by hand.
- Bills and Receipts 1947-1948 (Folder 2)
  This series contains bills, statements, and receipts for hospital services, supplies, and office rental. Bills are to both Porter and H. St. George Tucker which could suggest they shared an office.
- Journal Reprints
  This series contains reprints of articles listed by date.
  - Articles written by Porter. 1929-1951 (Folder 3.1)
    - Aqueous Extract of Liver (Folder 3.1)
      Journal of the American Medical Association, Vol. 93, July 20, 1929.
    - The Treatment of Nontropical Sprue with Liver Extract (Folder 3.1)
      American Journal of Medical Sciences, Vol. CLXXIX No. 3 March 1930.
    - The Heart in Typhoid Fever (Folder 3.1)
      The American Heart Journal, Vol. 10 No. 6 August 1935
    - The Heart in Endemic Pellagria (Folder 3.1)
      The Southern Medical Journal, Vol. 30 No.1 January 1937.
    - Heart Changes and Physiologic Adjustement in Hookworm Anemia (Folder 3.1)
      The American Heart Journal, Vol. 13 No. 5 May 1937.
    - The Significance of Cardiac Enlargement Caused by Arteriovenous Fistual (Folder 3.1)
      Annals of Internal Medicine, Vol. 11 No. 2 August, 1937.
    - Stereograms on Cirrhosis and Fatty Liver (Folder 3.1)
      Exhibit: Annual Meeting, American Medical Association, June 11-15, 1951.
  - Articles Written by Others 1909-1937
    - The Quarterly Journal of Medicine (Folder 5.2)
      Vol. 2 No.6 January, 1909
    - Die Malaria (Folder 5.2)
      Handbuch Der Speziellen Pathologischen Anatomie Und Histologie, Berlin 1926.
    - Deutsches Archiv fur Klinische Medizin (Folder 3.2)
      Leipzig 1927
    - Surgical Treatment of Cardiac Ischaemia (Folder 3.2)
      The Lancet, January 23, 1937
- American Council of Learned Societies. (Folder 4)
  This folder contains drafts of reports given at the meetings of the American Council of Learned Societies.
- Admissions Committee 1953-1960 (Folder 5)
  This series contains the papers of Dr. H. St. George Tucker, Jr. It contains candidate lists, request for applications, recommendations, and the decisions of the Medical College of Virginia admission committee.
  - Admissions Committee Records 1952-1953 (Folder 5.1)
  - Admissions Committee Records 1953-1954 (Folder 5.2)
  - Admissions Committee Records 1956 (Folder 5.3)
  - Admissions Committee Records 1957 (Folder 5.4)
  - Admissions Committee Records 1957-1958 (Folder 5.5)
  - Admissions Committee Records 1958-1959 (Folder 5.6)
  - Admissions Committee Reports 1960 (Folder 5.7)
- Privileges for Private Practice Committee 1941-1958 (Folder 6)
  This series contains the papers of Dr. Isaac Bigger and later, Dr H. St. George Tucker, Jr. It contains committee minutes, correspondence, and official paperwork of the privileges for private practice committee chaired by Bigger and Tucker.
  - Minutes and Official Business 1941-1954 (Folder 6.1)
  - Correspondence 1941-1954 (Folder 6.2)
    Folder 1
  - Correspondence 1941-1954 (Folder 6.3)
    Folder 2
  - Correspondence 1941-1954 (Folder 6.4)
    Folder 3
  - Committee Notes 1955-1958 (Folder 6.5)
  - Committee Notes 1955-1958 (Folder 6.6)
- Miscellaneous (Folder 7)
  This folder contains an assortment of clippings, magazines and other papers.
  - Boy Home Was Never Like This! Cries Lone Patient As He Rests in Splendor in Medical College Hospital January 16, 1941. (Folder 7)
    Richmond Times Dispatch
  - Virginia General Practice News Jan-Feb 1956 (Folder 7)
    Vol. 7 No. 1
  - The Scarab February 1960 (Folder 7)
    Vol. 9 No. 1
  - Curriculum Vitae (Folder 7)
    Lytt I. Gardner, MD.
- Photographs (Folder 8)
  This folder contains photographs found within the collection.
  - First Patient in New Hospital, 1941 1941 (Folder 8)
    Same photograph used in 1941 newspaper clipping.
  - Portrait photograph 1927 (Folder 8)
    Dr. Sparrell S. Gale